[Music]
garlic lowers blood pressure regulates
cholesterol and stimulates immunity I've
talked about the heart disease risk
factors what about the immunity eating
Garlic appears to offer The Best of Both
Worlds dampening the overactive face of
the immune system by suppressing
inflammation while boosting protective
immunity for example natural killer cell
immunity which our body uses to purge
cells that have been stricken by viruses
or cancer in World War II garlic was
evidently dubbed Russian penicillin
because after running out of antibiotics
that's what the Soviet government turned
to but does it actually work you don't
know until you put it to the test for
example how about preventing the common
cold perhaps the world's most widespread
viral infe infection with most people
suffering approximately 2 to five colds
per year the first double blind Placebo
control trial to investigate the
prevention of viral disease with a
garlic supplement those randomized to
the garlic suffered 60% fewer colds 70%
fewer days affected so not only fewer
colds but faster recovery suffering only
one and a half days instead of five so
accelerated relief reduction in symptom
some severity faster recovery to full
fitness okay but this study was done
nearly you know 20 years ago what about
all the other randomized control trials
there aren't any just that one trial to
date but still so and the best available
balance of evidence then suggest that
garlic May indeed prevent occurrences of
the common cold the common cold is one
thing but what about cancer right is it
a stake through the heart of cancer U
various garlic supplements have been
tested on cells in a Petri dish or or
lab animals uh but there were no human
studies to see garlic could affect gene
expression until now eat one big clove
of crushed raw garlic and within hours
you get an alteration of the expression
of your genes related to anti-cancer
immunity it's one thing to say a big
boost in production of cancer
suppressing proteins like encast Statin
when you drip garlic directly on sells
in a Petri dish but you also see boosted
gene expression directly in your
bloodstream within hours of eating it
does this then translate into lower
cancer risk 10 population studies put
together and those reporting higher
consumption of garlic only had half the
risk of stomach cancer how do you define
High uh and and each study it was
different from a few times a month to
every day but I mean regardless those
who ate more appear to have lower cancer
rates than those who ate less suggesting
a protective effect and hey stomach
cancer is a leading cause of cancer
related death around the world well
garlic is relatively cheap widely
available and easy to incorporate into
your daily diet in a safe Manner and
perhaps the more the better the only way
to prove garlic can prevent cancer
though is to put it to the test
thousands of individuals were randomized
to receive seven years of a garlic
supplement or Placebo and they did tend
to get less cancer and die from less
cancer but the findings were not
statistically significant meaning they
could have just happened by chance why
didn't we see a more definitive result
given that garlic eaters appear to have
such lower cancer rates well they didn't
give them garlic they gave them garlic
extract and oil pills it's possible some
of the purported Active Components
weren't preserved supplement form uh one
study of garlic supplements found that
it might take up to 27 capsules to
obtain the same amount of garlic
goodness found in just a half clove of
crushed raw garlic what happens if you
cook it if you compare raw chopped
garlic to garlic simmered for 15 minutes
boiled for six or stir fried for just
one minute you can get a threefold drop
and one of the purported active
ingredients called Allison when you boil
it even more if you simmer it for too
long
and it all seems to get wiped out by
even the minute of stir fry what about
roasted garlic surprisingly even though
roasting is hotter than boiling it
preserved about twice as much raw has
the most but it may be easier for some
folks to eat you know two or three
cloves of cooked garlic than even a half
clove of raw what about pickled garlic
or or those jars of minced garlic packed
in water or or packed in oil or that
fancy fermented black garlic though
Jarred garlic may be more convenient
there is comparably less garlicky
goodness especially pickled garlic and
the black garlic really Falls far behind
can you eat too much the garlic meta
analysis suggests there's no real safety
concerns with side effects or overdosing
though that's with internal use you
should not stick crushed garlic on your
skin it can cause irritation and if left
on long enough can actually burn you
wrap your knees with a garlic paste
bandage or stick some on your back
overnight and you can end up like this
or this definitely don't rub garlic on
babies but an article online said that
topical garlic was good for resid
disorders and the girl was
congested look at those blisters the
poor pump
natural does not necessarily mean safe
right don't put it on your toes don't
use it as a face mask don't use it to
try to get out of military service uh
but when you instead just eat it like
you're supposed to there shouldn't be a
problem though some people do get an
upset tummy if they eat a little too
much and look you really can't say no
side effects given the body odor and
garlic breath
[Music]